<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Adam Drewery's Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[Adam Drewery's Blog]]></description><link>blog.drewery.uk</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 08:13:30 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/adam-drewery/blog/main/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 08:13:30 GMT</pubDate><language><![CDATA[en]]></language><managingEditor><![CDATA[Adam Drewery]]></managingEditor><webMaster><![CDATA[Adam Drewery]]></webMaster><item><title><![CDATA[How I Set up a Blog in GitHub Pages using Blazor WASM]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h1 id="setting-up-a-blog-in-github-pages-using-blazor-wasm">Setting up a blog in GitHub Pages using Blazor WASM</h1>
<p>I achieved a blogception by creating a blog then blogging about the blog from within the blog itself. This is what I&#39;ve decided to refer to as &quot;recursive metablogging&quot;.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I&#39;m not sure how often I&#39;ll post, but I&#39;ll try to keep it regular. I&#39;m also not sure what I&#39;ll post about, but I&#39;ll try to keep it interesting. I&#39;m also not sure how long I&#39;ll keep this up, but I&#39;ll try to keep it going for a while.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>- This is what github copilot suggested I should write next</em></p>
<hr>
<h2 id="getting-started">Getting started</h2>
<p>Its crazy easy to make a page on GitHub pages. You just create a repo, click a button, then you&#39;re off. Well, sort of anyway. I also wanted to write something myself using Blazor, because I&#39;m really into Blazor these days. Its not quite as simple as just deploying a bunch of HTML though.</p>
<h3 id="the-first-step">The first step</h3>
<p>Obviously the first step was to create a blazor project.</p>
<pre><code class="language-shell">dotnet new blazorwasm -o blog
</code></pre>
<p>I paid for some overpriced crappy template to get me started because my frontend skills aren&#39;t great. By the end though, I&#39;d changed almost everything about it. Anyway, after shimmying that into the blazor project it was ready to push up to the repo.</p>
<h3 id="configure-github-pages">Configure GitHub Pages</h3>
<p>By default, GitHub page sites are deployed from the master branch. Obviously this isn&#39;t going to work with a blazor project, we need to get it all compiled up first. So first thing I did was change the deployment method in github to &quot;GitHub Actions&quot;.</p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/adam-drewery/blog/main/content/making-a-blog/setup-github-pages.png" alt="configuring github pages" title="configuring github pages"></p>
<p>At this point I also got the domain name set up, the instructions tell you exactly what to do and it takes about 2 minutes. Plus, I enabled HTTPS-only while I was in here for security and privacy reasons.</p>
<h3 id="set-up-the-pipeline">Set up the pipeline</h3>
<p>I&#39;ve not used GitHub actions very much, but I&#39;ve used Azure DevOps a lot and turns out they&#39;re pretty similar. I just needed to create a new workflow file in the .github/workflows folder. I called it &quot;build.yml&quot; because I&#39;m not very creative.</p>
<p>I started with a regular .NET build and publish. To anyone who&#39;s compiled a .net app before it should be self explanitory:</p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml">jobs:
  build:
    permissions:
      pages: write
      id-token: write
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    steps:
    
    - uses: actions/checkout@v2
    
    - name: Setup .NET
      uses: actions/setup-dotnet@v3
      with:
        dotnet-version: 7.0.x
          
    - name: .NET Publish
      run: dotnet publish site/blog.csproj -c Release -o release --nologo
</code></pre>
<p>Note the <code>permissions</code> section. While I&#39;d given GitHub Actions read and write permissions in its settings, it turns out that wasn&#39;t enough, and I continued to receive errors during the build. This section fixed that.</p>
<p>I added this part to ensure that GitHub pages was enabled and configured correctly:</p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml">    - name: Configure Pages
      uses: actions/configure-pages@v3
</code></pre>
<p>By default, GitHub pages assumes your page is being deployed via Jekyll. Since this isn&#39;t the case here, we have to tell GitHub to specifically not do that. Which is kind of weird, but hey, its an easy fix:</p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml">    - name: Disable Jekyll
      run: touch release/wwwroot/.nojekyll
</code></pre>
<p>Then, I added a step to upload the release folder as an artifact. It seems like this is what GitHub actions needs in order to do the deployment. </p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml">    - name: Upload artifact
      uses: actions/upload-artifact@v2
      with:
        name: wwwroot
        path: &#39;./release/wwwroot&#39;
</code></pre>
<p>So, that was the build job. But what about the release part? I got you covered:</p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml">  deploy:
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    needs: build
    permissions:
      pages: write
      id-token: write
    environment:
      name: GitHub Pages
      url: ${{ steps.deployment.outputs.page_url }}
    steps:      
    - name: Deploy to GitHub Pages
      id: deployment
      uses: actions/deploy-pages@v2
</code></pre>
<p>Here you can see it uses the same <code>permissions</code> block as in the build job. I also added an <code>environment</code> block to give it a name and a URL.</p>
<p>Other than that though the release part is really simple. It gets the artifact we uploaded in the previous job and yeets it into GitHub pages, easy peasy.</p>
<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/adam-drewery/blog/main/content/making-a-blog/build-github-pages.png" alt="configuring github actions" title="configuring github actions"></p>
<hr>
<h3 id="fix-the-paths">Fix the paths</h3>
<p>Using that pipeline, we can successfully deploy the site. With a few caveats...</p>
<p>Firstly, the site is deployed to a subfolder. So, instead of being at <code>https://adam-drewery.github.io</code> it was at <code>https://adam-drewery.github.io/blog</code>. This is because the repo is called &quot;blog&quot; and that&#39;s the name of the folder the site is deployed to.</p>
<p>This is a problem because your scripts and styles etc will be looking at <code>adam-drewery.github.io/script.js</code>, whereas it is actualy located in the subfolder <code>adam-drewery.github.io/blog/script.js</code> (emphasis on the <code>/blog/</code> bit).</p>
<p>My solution to this was simply to configure a domain name to host from (in this case, blog.drewery.uk) However, for anyone not using a domain name, and hosting on the default github.io address, its important to ensure your script and style paths are all relative, and that you add a <code>base</code> tag to the head of the index.html file like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-html">&lt;base href=&quot;/blog/&quot; /&gt;
</code></pre>
<h3 id="fix-the-routing">Fix the routing</h3>
<p>The other problem I had was that the routing wasn&#39;t working. I could navigate to the root of the site, but any other page would just return a 404. This is because the routing is handled by the blazor runtime, and the blazor runtime included in <code>index.html</code>.</p>
<p>So, I added a step to the build job to copy the index page to <code>404.html</code>, which GitHub pages will use as the 404 page.</p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml">    - name: copy index.html to 404.html
      run: cp site/wwwroot/index.html site/wwwroot/404.html
</code></pre>
<p>Probably doesn&#39;t require too much explanation as to what&#39;s going on here... its pretty filthy though, I felt like I had to take a shower afterwards. I wish there was a better way to do this.</p>
<p>But anyway, if its stupid and it works, then its not stupid! So, I&#39;m happy with it. You can see the completed pipeline yaml file <a href="https://github.com/adam-drewery/blog/blob/main/.github/workflows/build.yml">here</a>.</p>
<p>I&#39;ll write another post at some point describing how I built the site itself. I had quite a bit of fun with it if I&#39;m honest... frontend development has gotten more enjoyable now I can delegate the tedious bits to ChatGPT. 😎</p>
]]></description><link>https://blog.drewery.uk/making-a-blog</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.drewery.uk/making-a-blog</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam Drewery]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Invalid Date</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The registry of singletons pattern, a.k.a. why all my homies hate enums]]></title><description><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-registry-of-singletons-pattern">The registry of singletons pattern</h1>
<h4 id="aka-why-all-my-homies-hate-enums">AKA why all my homies hate enums.</h4>
<p>Enums are great. Well, they&#39;re OK anyway. Its a nice thing to be able to assign labels to numbers but that&#39;s about all they&#39;re good for. They&#39;re not very extensible, and they&#39;re not very encapsulated. </p>
<h3 id="the-problem">The problem</h3>
<p>Oftentimes I&#39;ve seen an innocent looking enum defined and used like this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-csharp">public enum Country
{
    Germany,
    France,
    Mexico
}

public class Person
{
    public string Name { get; set; }

    public Country Country { get; set; }
}
</code></pre>
<p>Everything seems alright so far. I can create a person and set their country to Germany. But inevitably, we end up needing to perform some sort of logic relating to this enum. And, since enums cannot contain logic, we inevitably end up with at least one, but often more, switch statements littered throughout our codebase: </p>
<pre><code class="language-csharp">
public int GetSalesTaxRate(Person person)
{
    switch(person.Country)
    {
        case Country.Germany:
            return 19;
        case Country.France:
            return 20;
        case Country.Mexico:
            return 16;
    }
}
</code></pre>
<p>The major problem here is a lack of encapsulation. This also violates the open/closed principle, because if we need to add a new country, we have to go and modify this method, and all the other ones which operate on the <code>Country</code> property of a person. It should be pretty clear why this is a problem...</p>
<h3 id="the-solution">The solution</h3>
<p>This is a variation of the &quot;Registry of Singletons&quot; pattern. We can see it in use in the .NET framework itself, for example in the <code>System.Drawing.Color</code> class and <code>System.Text.Encoding</code>, to name a couple.</p>
<p>For starters we need a class, with a private constructor:</p>
<pre><code class="language-csharp">public class Country
{
    private Country(string name, int salesTaxRate)
    {
        Name = name;
        SalesTaxRate = salesTaxRate;
    }

    public string Name { get; }

    public int SalesTaxRate { get; }
}
</code></pre>
<p>We make the constructor private so clients cannot accidentally add new countries. We also make the properties read-only, so they cannot be modified after the object is created. Next we just add our countries as static properties:</p>
<pre><code class="language-csharp">public class Country
{
    private Country(string name, int salesTaxRate)
    {
        Name = name;
        SalesTaxRate = salesTaxRate;
    }

    public string Name { get; }

    public int SalesTaxRate { get; }

    public static Country Germany { get; } = new Country(&quot;Germany&quot;, 19);

    public static Country France { get; } = new Country(&quot;France&quot;, 20);

    public static Country Mexico { get; } = new Country(&quot;Mexico&quot;, 16);
}
</code></pre>
<p>Hey presto! It works just like an enum. In fact, sometimes people might not even realise its not an enum. But now we can access rich data about the countries, and its impossible to add new countries without also being forced to include required information such as the sales tax rate.</p>
<h3 id="exposing-it-as-an-ienumerable">Exposing it as an <code>IEnumerable</code></h3>
<p>Sometimes we want to expose our list of countries as an <code>IEnumerable</code> and be able to look them up by name. This is easy to do with a static property that uses reflection:</p>
<pre><code class="language-csharp">    public static IDictionary&lt;string, Country&gt; All =&gt; typeof(Country)
        .GetProperties(BindingFlags.Public | BindingFlags.Static)
        .Where(p =&gt; p.PropertyType == typeof(Country))
        .Select(p =&gt; p.GetValue(null))
        .Cast&lt;Country&gt;()
        .ToDictionary(c =&gt; c.Name, c =&gt; c);
}
</code></pre>
<p>If you write a lot of these types of classes, it might even save you time to put this into an extension method or base class.</p>
<h3 id="but-what-about-serialization">But what about serialization?</h3>
<p>Its nice to have these rich objects, but sometimes we need to serialize them. For example, if we&#39;re sending them over the wire, or storing them in a database.</p>
<p>A custom JSON converter may feel like a lot of work but it really isn&#39;t. This one will work specifically for the <code>Country</code> class we defined above, however, if you choose to implement these with a base class or interface, you can make a generic version of this converter that will work for all of them.</p>
<pre><code class="language-csharp:">
public class CountryConverter : JsonConverter
{
    public override bool CanConvert(Type objectType)
    {
        return objectType == typeof(Country);
    }

    public override object ReadJson(JsonReader reader, Type objectType, object existingValue, JsonSerializer serializer)
    {
        JObject jsonObject = JObject.Load(reader);
        string name = jsonObject.Value&lt;string&gt;();
        return Country.All[name];
    }

    public override void WriteJson(JsonWriter writer, object value, JsonSerializer serializer)
    {
        Country country = (Country)value;
        writer.WriteValue(country.Name);
    }
}
</code></pre>
<p>And that&#39;s it! Now you have a fully encapsulated enum-like object that can be serialized and deserialized, and you can add as many properties and methods as you like to it. Maybe you have some ideas on how this pattern could be improved? Let me know!</p>
]]></description><link>https://blog.drewery.uk/registry-of-singletons</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://blog.drewery.uk/registry-of-singletons</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Adam Drewery]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>